Guide to the Malcolm Whyte papers and Troubador Press Publications, ca. 1963-1995
Whyte, Malcolm papers, and Troubador Press Publications, ca. 1963-1995
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Malcolm Whyte papers and Troubador Press publications, 1963-1995
4411
Malcolm Whyte
4.6 cubic ft.
Books, documents.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Children's books by various authors, published by Troubador Press, Troubador Press catalogs and other documents including book files, history of Troubador Press and job cards.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE and ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Troubador Press is owned and operated in San Francisco, California by Malcolm Whyte. Whyte graduated from Cornell University in 1955.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Children's books including coloring, cut-out, game, and puzzle books by various authors including Malcolm Whyte and Larry Evans, published by Troubador Press. Also, an Edward Gorey book designed by Whyte, a Great Plains Indians cut-out book, a guidebook for Cornellians in San Francisco, and Troubador Press catalogs and documents demonstrating the step-by-step production of one of the books.
Toss Your Own Ticker Tape Parade and Super Hero Kit by Malcolm Whyte, published by Andrews McMeel Publishing.
Also, additional book files and history of Troubador Press.
"Job cards" documenting the cost of producing various Troubador books and other printing jobs; also, cards regarding the printing of City Lights Publication's books, including 9 printings of Allen Ginsberg's HOWL in which Troubador replaced, at the publisher Lawrence Ferlinghetti's request, the "dirty words" represented only with ellipses with the words as written in Ginsberg's original manuscript.
"Toot-Your-Own-Horn" art, original roughs, manuscripts, correspondence, and kit content examples (1964-1966).
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Books are listed alphabetically by author with the following notations:
c - calligraphy by
cr - created by
d - designed by
e - edited by
i - illustrated by
w - written by
SUBJECTS
Names:
Whyte, Malcolm.; Evans, Larry, 1939-; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Gorey, Edward, 1925-; Troubador Press.
Subjects:
Children's literature.
Places:
San Francsico (Calif.), Description and travel.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Books, publications and kits
Box 1-5
Series II. Files and documents
Box 4, 6-9
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Books, publications and kits
  - The Enchanted Kingdom, Abrams, Jodell (i and w) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Enchanted Forest, Abrams, Jodell (w, i) (Box 11)
  - Coloring Album of Los Angeles, Abrams, Jodell and Edward J. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Wilson's Andersen, Andersen, Hans Christian (w) and S. Clay Wilson (i) (Box 3)
  - 50 Years of Cars to Color, Fold & Display, Arceneaux, Marc ( i and d) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Graphics, Computer Crosswords, Armbruster, Frank and D.K.Holland (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Paper Alien Star Ships To Cut-out and Fly, Bae, Yoong (d, i) (Box 11)
  - Paper UFO, Bae, Yoong (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Paper Star Ships, Bae, Yoong (i and d) (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Paper Robots, Bae, Yoong (d and i) (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Pinwheels to Color, Cut-out and Spin, Bae, Yoong (d & i) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Paper Rockets to Color, Cut-Out and Fly, Bae, Yoong (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Great Comic Cats, Blackbeard, Bill and Malcolm Whyte (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A Child's American Heritage, Blocksom, Claudia (w & i) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Horse Show Paper Dolls, Boyd, Leanne Carson (w) and Malcolm Whyte (e) (Box 4)
  - Mammoth Coloring Album, Bridges, Dennis (i and w) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pogo's Golden Anniversary Exhibition, Burstein, Mark (w), Selby Kelly (w), and Steve Thompson (w) (Box 1)
  - The Original Old Radio Game, Callahan, Ed, Bill Shilling, and Mal Whyte (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Everything for Your Birthday Party, Chad (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - An Outstanding Collection of 3-Dimensional Drawings & Stereo Views, Chandler, Arthur and Wayne Pope (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - It's Your World - a basic ecology guide and project book, Chargin, Claudia (w & i)
  - Good Times America Coloring Album, Davenport, Chris (d) and Kimberly Knoll (i) (Box 4)
  - Double-ups - Hidden Pictures to Color and Solve, Davenport, Marilyn (i and w) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Butterflies and Moths, deTreville, Stan (i) and deTreville, Susan (w) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reptiles and Amphibians, deTreville, Stan (i) and deTreville, Susan (w) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - A Color & Story Album for Horse Lovers, Dian, Twila (w and i) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Draw Your Own Monsters, Duhnam, Laura (Box 11)
  - Maze Craze 4, Duncan, Charles (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Heather's Horse Race, Dunn, Anna (i) and Carroll Killingsworth (w) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Once Upon a Time, Dunn, Anna (i) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 3-Dimensional Monster Mazes, Evans, Larry (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 3-Dimensional Mazes, Evans, Larry (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 3-Dimensional Mazes, Volume II, Evans, Larry (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gross and Gruesome Games and Puzzles, Evans, Larry (Box 11)
  - How to Draw Monsters, Evans, Larry (w & i) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - How to Draw Prehistoric Monsters, Evans, Larry (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - How to Draw Robots and Spaceships, Evans, Larry (w & i) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Invisibles - Hidden Picture Puzzles, Evans, Larry (w & i) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Invisibles - Hidden Picture Puzzles Two, Evans, Larry (w & i) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pyramid Puzzles, Evans, Larry (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gnomes Games, Evans, Larry (d) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 3-Dimensional Maze Art, Evans, Larry (w & i) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 3-Dimensional Optical Illusions to Color & Construct, Evans, Larry (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mammoth Coloring Album, (1978); Evans, Larry (i) and Bridges, Dennis (w), (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Giant 3-Dimensional Maze - Fantastic Journey, Evans, Larry (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Largest 3-Dimensional Maze in the Universe - City of Tomorrow, Evans, Larry (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Maze Cubes, Evans, Larry (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Most Gigantic 3-Dimensional Maze in the Galaxy, Evans, Larry (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Victorian Puzzles, Evans, Larry (Box 4)
  - Cowboys, Fleischman, Chas (i) and Helberg, Kristin (w) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Aesop's Fable, Foster, Brad (i) and Townsend, George Fyler (w) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Space WARP (Warrior Activated Robot Patrol), Fox, Frank (i and cr) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Travels with Farley, Frank, Phil (Box 4)
  - San Francisco Scenes, Frazer, Greg (w) and Phil Frank (i) (Box 4)
  - Zap to Zippy, Geerdes, Clay (w) and Malcolm Whyte (w) (Box 1)
  - Color & Applique, Georgia Ball Originals (Box 3)
  - Gorey Cats, Gorey, Edward (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Color and Puzzle, Heller, Ruth (d) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Color and Puzzle, Heller, Ruth (designer) (Box 3)
  - Maze Craze, Heller, Ruth (designer) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Color and Stitch, Heller, Ruth (Box 3)
  - think metrics, Holland, D.K. and Melinda Wentzell (graphics) and F.O. Armbruster (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Maze Craze 3, Hull, John (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Maze Craze 2, Hull, John (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Puzzlers, Hull, John (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - The Official Advanced Dungeons & Dragons Coloring Album, Irons, Greg (i) and Gygax, Gary (w) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Famous Monsters Funbook, Johnson, William R. (i and w) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Famous Monsters Funbook, Johnson, William R. (i and w) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dinosaur Funbook, Johnson, William R. (writer and illustrator) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Beasties Coloring Book, Koski, Vernon (i) and Whyte, Malcolm (w) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Ballet, Kinic, Helen (i) and Tichenor, Kay (w) (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Three Pigs a Story Book with Puppets, Littin, Elizabeth (w) and Jon Worden (i) (Box 4)
  - Nature's Pets, Mace, Varian (i) and John Kipping (w) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Nature Crafts & Projects, Mace, Varian (i) and Beverly Frazier (w) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The Meanings of Christmas, Mace, Varian (i) and Malcolm Whyte (w) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fairy Tales Color & Story Album, Mace, Varian (i) and Ann Moen (w) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Small World Cook & Color Book, Mace, Varian (i) and Beverly Frazier (w) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Dinosaur Masks and Puppets, Mah, Ronald (Box 4)
  - Magic Tricks, Marks, Burton (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - The Puggle Tales Coloring & Adventure Book, Mendez, Phil (i) and Barrett, John (w) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Mother Goose Coloring Album, Mills, Elizabeth (Box 4)
  - Huggs & Cuddles Teddy Bear Paper Dolls, Muzick, Terra (i) and Whyte, Malcolm (w) (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Auto Racing, Nebeker, Albert (i) and Eckman, James & Terry Wilson (w) (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Bears Color & Story Book, Nolan Dennis (I) and Schiller, Karen (w) (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Geometric Playthings to Color, Cut and Fold, Pedersen, Jean J. and Kent A. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Gnomes Color and Story, Poortvliet, Rien (i) and Huygen, Wil (w) (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Mother Earth's House Plant, Rapp, Lynn and Joel (w) and Rita Warner (i) (Box 4)
  - Zodiac Coloring Book, Redmond, Dennis (i) (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Mona Lisa Coloring Book, Redmond, Dennis (i) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Flashback Fashion Paper Dolls, Robbins, Trina (i and w) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - North American Wildflowers, Saijo, Gompers (i) and Kipping, John L. (w) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Jungle, Saijo, Gompers (i) and Kipping, John L. (w) (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - The Occult Coloring Book, Saijo, Gompers (i) and Garvin, Richard M. (w) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - The Occult Coloring Book, Saijo, Gompers (i) and Garvin, Richard M. (w) (Box 3)
  - North American Sea Life, Saijo, Gompers (i) and Whyte, Mal (e) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - North American Bird Life, Saijo, Gompers (i) and Whyte, Mal (e) (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - North American Wildlife, Saijo, Gompers (i) and Mal Whyte (editor) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Monster Gallery, Savee, Mark (i) and Woskey, Leah (w) (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Science Fiction Anthology, Savee, Mark (i) and Ken (w) (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - International Folk Crafts, Schields, Gretchen (i) and Ginger Scribner (w) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Marvels of the Deep Sea, Schot, Glenn (w and i) (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Hot Air Balloons Coloring Album, Senum, Marilyn (i and w) (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Giants & Gnomes, Slaton, Lana (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Horses in History Coloring Album, Slaton, Lana (Box 4)
  - Fat Cat's Craft and Coloring Book, Sloan, Donna (i) and Karen Whyte (w) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Fat Cat Coloring & Limerick Book, Sloan, Donna (i) and Whyte, Mal (w) (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - The Love Bug Coloring & Limerick Book, Sloan, Donna (i) and Whyte, Mal (w) (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Fat Cat's Cookbook, Sloan, Donna (i) and Karen Whyte (w) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - African Safari, Smith, Daniel (i & d) and Malcolm Whyte (w) (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Prehistoric Animals, Smith, Daniel (i & d) and Malcolm Whyte (w) (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Kachinas Color and Cut-Out Collection, Staheli, Julie West (adapted from Hopi originals) (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Kachina Dolls Color and Cut-Out Collection, Staheli, Julie West (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Monster Movie Game, Stanley, John and Mal Whyte (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Windows of Nature - a story-coloring book, Stillwater, Maitreya (w & i) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Fashion Kit Design & Color Paper Doll, Sullivan, Maria (i and w) (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Dolls Through the Ages, Swanberg, Nancie (i and w) (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Toys Through the Ages, Swanberg, Nancie (i and w) (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Great Ballet Paper Dolls, Swanberg, Nancie (w and i) (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Butterflies - A Colors of Nature Book, Tachiera, Andrea, (i) and Malcolm Whyte (w) (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Farm Animals - A Colors of Nature Book, Tachiera, Andrea (i) and Malcolm Whyte (w) (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Sea Creaturse - A Colors of Nature Book, Tachiera, Andrea (i) and Malcolm Whyte (w) (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Zoo Animals - A Colors of Nature Book, Tachiera, Andrea (i) and Malcolm Whyte (w) (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Tales of Fantasy, Todd, Larry (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - The Dinosaur Coloring Book, Tong, Winston (i) (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Black and White Coloring Book, Turner, Morrie (i) and Letha (w) (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - The Old Testament - A story to read and color, Uzilevsky, Marcus (i and c) (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - New York Scenes, Uzilevsky, Marcus John (i) and Melissa Uzilevsky and Ida McClelland (w) (Box 4)
  - The New Testament - a story to read and color, Uzilevsky, Marcus (i and c) (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - North American Indians, Warner, Rita (i) and Fox, Frank (w) (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Cats & Kittens Coloring Album, Warner, Rita (i) and Kunic, Debbie (w) (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Dogs & Puppies Coloring Album, Warner, Rita (i) (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Wonderful World of Horses Coloring Album, Warner, Rita (i and w) (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - The Big Book of Board Games, Weinert, Fifi and Tom Beaudrot (i) and Laura Palmer (w) (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Ready-to-Make Photo & Scene Machines, Wentz, Budd (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Paper Movie Machines, Wentz, Budd (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Optricks, a Book of Optical Illusions, Wentzell, Melinda and D.K. Holland (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Optricks 2, Wentzell, Melinda and D. K. Holland (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Kid's Natural Foods Party and Picnic Cook and Coloring Book, Whyte, Karen (w) and Donna Sloan (i) (Box 4)
  - Troubador Treasury, Whyte, Malcolm (e) (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Gnomes Funbook, Whyte, Malcolm (e) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Wild Wild West: Puzzles and Games Funbook (2 copies), Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Larry Evans (i) (Box 3)
  - Oceans of Invisibles Hidden Picture Funbook (2 copies), Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Larry Evans (i) (Box 3)
  - Super Hero Kit, Whyte, Malcolm (Box 3)
  - Toss Your Own Ticker Tape Parade, Whyte, Malcolm (Box 3)
  - Dolphins and Whales Model Set (2 copies), Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Daniel Smith (i) (Box 5)
  - Dolphins and Whales Model Set typeset and printer's press proofs, Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Daniel Smith (i) (Box 5)
  - The Great Whales Coloring Album, Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Daniel Smith (i) (Box 4)
  - The Dinosaur Action Set, Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Daniel Smith (i) (Box 4)
  - The Dinosaur Action Set Book Two, Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Daniel Smith (i) (Box 4)
  - The Undersea Dinosaur Action Set, Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Daniel Smith (i) (Box 4)
  - Farm Animals A Colors of Nature Book, Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Andrea Tachiera (i) (Box 4)
  - Zoo Animals A Colors of Nature Book, Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Andrea Tachiera (i) (Box 4)
  - Sea Creatures A Colors of Nature Book, Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Andrea Tachiera (i) (Box 4)
  - Butterflies A Colors of Nature Book, Whyte, Malcolm (w) and Andrea Tachiera (i) (Box 4)
  - Exotic Animals, Whyte, Malcolm (w), Alice Carter (i) (Box 11)
  - Tropical Fish, Whyte, Malcolm (w), Andrea Tachiera (i) (Box 11)
  - Great Plains Indians, action set, Whyte, Malcolm (w), Daniel Smith (d), Chin-Han Hsu (i) (Box 11)
  - Zoo Animals, action set: Africa, Southeast Asian, Australia, Artic, Whyte, Malcolm (w), Daniel Smith (i) (Box 11)
  - Zoo Animals, action set 2: Asian, South America, Africa, North America, Whyte, Malcolm (w), Daniel Smith (i) (Box 11)
  - Teddy Bear Fun Book, Whyte, Malcolm (w), Maryanne Regal Hoburg (i) (Box 11)
  - Travels with the Happy Bears, paper dolls, Whyte, Malcolm (w), Terra Muzik (i) (Box 11)
  - Toot-Your-Own-Horn Kits, Whyte, Malcolm (cr) and Joe Bacal (cr) (Box 10)
  - Wilson's Grimm (2 copies), Wilson, S. Clay (i) (Box 4)
  - Color & Quilt, Zwanck, Alice (Box 3)
  - Paper Airplanes & Adventure Book, (no author) (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Mother Goose's Picture Puzzles A Book for Children, Combining Quaint Drawings, Hidden Objects in each Picture, and Nursery Jingles, (no author) (Box 4)
  - Zodiac Sign-In Book: Record Your Friends' Autographs and Birthdays on their Zodiac Sign., (no author) (Box 4)
- Series II. Files and documents
  - Troubador Book Ideas Speech and other biographical information (Box 4)
  - Troubador Press catalogs, 1974-1984 (Box 4)
  - History of Troubador Press, including sales, catalogs and publicity, ca. 1960's-1990's (Box 6)
  - Additional history material, ca. 1960's-1990's (Box 7)
  - Book files A-P, ca. 1980's-1990's (Box 7)
  - Book files P-Z, ca. 1980's-1990's (Box 8)
  - Additional book files, ca. 1980's-1990's (Box 8)
  - Job cards, 1968-1982, 1990's (Box 9)